<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mock-majesty: or, the siege of Munster. Being a true story of those fine things, wherewith King Iohn Becock, at first a botcher of Leiden by profession, and his companions the Anabaptists, pleased themselves after they were become masters of that city. You shall here likewise have the issue of the whole mock-show. Imprimatur, James Cranford.</title>
            <author>Phillippson, J.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90669</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E270_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212338</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99870968</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99870968</idno>
            <idno type="VID">123366</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90669)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123366)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 45:E270[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mock-majesty: or, the siege of Munster. Being a true story of those fine things, wherewith King Iohn Becock, at first a botcher of Leiden by profession, and his companions the Anabaptists, pleased themselves after they were become masters of that city. You shall here likewise have the issue of the whole mock-show. Imprimatur, James Cranford.</title>
                  <author>Phillippson, J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J.S. and L.C.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644 [i.e. 1645]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to J. Phillippson by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Wing has publication year 1644[5]; Thomason catalogue lists under 1645.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 24th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123366:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123366:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MOCK-MAJESTY: OR, The ſiege of Munſter.</p>
            <p>BEING A TRUE STORY OF THOSE fine things, wherewith King IOHN BECOCK, At firſt a Botcher of <hi>Leiden</hi> by profeſſion, and his companions the ANABAPTISTS, pleaſed themſelves after they were become Maſters of that City.</p>
            <p>You ſhall here likewiſe have the iſſue of the whole <hi>MOCK-SHOW.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>C. TACITUS.</hi>
               </bibl> Quidam, ut imperium ſubvertant, libertatem proferunt; ſi ſubverterint, ipſam aggredientur.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Idem, Hiſtor. lib. 1.</hi>
               </bibl> Malignitati falſa ſpecies libertatis ineſt.</q>
            <p>ELEUTHEROPOLI, <hi>ANNO</hi> 'ΑΝΑΒΑΠΤΙΣΤΟΜΑΝΙ'ΑΣ, C.XIIX.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>James Cranford.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>L. C.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:123366:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123366:2"/>
            <p>TO THE WORSHIPFULL, Mr. RICHARD LITHGOLD, Mr. JOHN CHILD, Bailiffs of the ancient Corporation of <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Thames:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For their endeavour for the <hi>publique good;</hi> For their <hi>vigilancy</hi> in their Place, and Office:</p>
            <p>Eſpecially, For the aſſiſtance, and <hi>encouragement,</hi> of their <hi>Miniſter,</hi> in preaching the <hi>Word,</hi> and ſuppreſſing <hi>novell Fancies:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THIS IS DEDICATED, Willingly, Deſervedly.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:123366:3"/>
            <head>TO THE INTELLIGENT <hi>READER,</hi> Baptiſ'd, <hi>or</hi> Rantiſ'd.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou muſt excuſe me for this pretty new ſtampt word. It is pitty but it ſhould ſignifie ſomething in Engliſh. Whether it do or no, it is not a weeke ſince I firſt met with it, and that in a way of ſcorn, and contempt, of the</hi> Baptiſme <hi>of our Church.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ch. Blackwood <hi>in his booke entituled,</hi> The storming of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt in his two ſtrongeſt holds, &amp;c. <hi>very lately publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>He that goes about to naturalize it, and make it a</hi> Denizen, <hi>is one that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>kes upon him alſo to queſtion the truth of that</hi> Relation, <hi>which we have in</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Joan. Sleid. Commentarie X.</note> Sleidans commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>concerning</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Blackwood praef. pag. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> the tumultuous carriage of the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> in Germany, <hi>as himſelfe ſpeakes; making the Author thereof, for differing opinions ſake in matter of Religion, to make no conſcience of violating that ſacred rule, which directs and binds every Noble Hiſtorian,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ne quid falſi audeat; nequid veri non audeat.</note> That he dare ſpeake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing falſe; nor yet conceale any thing that is true. <hi>Not a little troubled to ſee ſo injurious, and falſe an imputation, laid upon the trueſt Hiſtory; that ever was written ſince the</hi> Acts of the Apoſtles; <hi>I was the more incited, to communicate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the publique view, and that in a language which we all can underſtand, that part thereof, which concerns thoſe tumults more eſpecially: and I do looke for better grounds, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing thereof, then ſuch weake ſurmiſes, and exceptions, that
<pb facs="tcp:123366:3"/>he was</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Blackwood,</hi> b. p. 12.</note> a contrary minded Hiſtorian; <hi>or, that</hi> (d) it is not lawfull to believe an Hiſtory, from the mouth, or pen, of an enemy. <hi>More Chriſtian, and rationall charity,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 4.16.</note>
               <hi>I am ſure, hath been obſerved to direct the ſoules and actions, even of Heathen men themſelves. And I forbeare not to make uſe of St.</hi> Pauls <hi>queſtion herein:</hi> Is he therefore become your enemy, <hi>becauſe he ſpeaks the truth? As for our Author, he hath as faithfully, as ever did any, obſerv'd what the</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Fl. Joſeph. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Appion. lib <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Herodian. l <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt of the</hi> Jewes <hi>requires in a good Hiſtorian,</hi> To relate nothing, which he could not maintaine from his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and certaine knowledge thereof, by <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tot rerum, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> geſſerat, aut à fide dignis acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat, notitiâ fretus, Comment. ſcribere aggreſſus eſt.</hi> Thuan. lib. 17, de Sleidano. <hi>Vid.</hi> Meich. Adamum. in Philoſoph. German. in <hi>Sleidano.</hi>
               </note> perſonall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in the action; or elſe had not received it from the hands of ſuch, whoſe truth ought not to be call'd into queſtion. <hi>What, in this reſpect, is objected againſt him by</hi> Matthaeus<note n="h" place="margin">Orat. de Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at uſu Hiſtor.</note> Dreſſerus, <hi>upon the bare word, and aſſertion, of his friend</hi> Chriſtop. Carlevilius, <hi>hath as much weight in it, as Mr.</hi> Blackwoods <hi>ſurmiſes. And of what ſpirit</hi> Dreſſerus <hi>was, learned men, who have peruſed his books, certainly cannot be ignorant. Onely I am ſorry, to ſee any Reformer joyne, or at leaſt, agree with ſo great a ſtickler for the Sea of</hi> Rome; <hi>and that in a cenſure againſt a Proteſtant, of ſuch known piety and integrity. It is hard to gain-ſay what the noon-day looks upon and witneſſes: And now to deny, what our fore-fathers, and all Chriſtendome well-neere tooke notice of, with no leſſe wonder then ſhame, were to endevour to ſwagger truth out of the world. The great reſpect and entertainment, which</hi> Sleidan <hi>had here, when he was</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Jo. Sleidanus in Anglia communi Proteſtantium nomine legationem obiit, <hi>Theod. Beza in Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Embaſadour to the Court of</hi> England <hi>in the generall name of all the Proteſtants of</hi> Germany, <hi>ſhal be both a teſtimony of his prudence, faithfulneſſe, and other abilities in pablique affaires; and alſo an aſſurance, that this</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>or fragment, of that his moſt excellent Hiſtory, ſhall find welcome
<pb facs="tcp:123366:4"/>with us in an Engliſh, though ſomewhat a courſer dreſſe. How ſacred and venerable he eſteemed</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Diligentiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimè fimul &amp; <hi>veriſſimè</hi> hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria perſcripta. <hi>Beza, ibid.</hi> Hiſtoriam huc illuc uſque <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acta fide,</hi> &amp; dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentrâ pertex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anus <hi>An.</hi> M.D.LVI. <hi>v. Geſner. in Biblioth. Henr. Pantaleon. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopograph. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; alios ſexcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>truth to be, and how re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious a thing he accounted it to ſwerve in the leaſt matter from the nice obſerving of it, if any man be not Chriſtian e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to have charity to believe the man himſelfe herein, others then in this caſe ſhall more then aboundantly witneſſe it.</hi> Thuanus, <hi>(k)</hi> Beza, &amp;c. <hi>Papiſts, Calviniſts, Lutherans, and men of what Religion ſoever, that are not yet more blinded by faction, then led by reaſon, will give ſatisfaction in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, even to ſuch as are extreamly ſcrupulous. And if all theſe will not worke in Mr.</hi> Blackwood <hi>a beliefe of</hi> Sleidans <hi>truth, in reſpect of this Relation, then let his owne name-ſake, and Countreyman, and perhaps kinſman,</hi>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. De Vinculo Relig. &amp; Imp.</note> Adam Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, <note n="(l)" place="margin">Omnia nudè, ſimpliciter, &amp; bonâ fiderprout quaeque res acta fuit, re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ito: nec enim de meo quicquam addo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nec in ullius hominis invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam, aut gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlam aliquid ſcribo. Ego ſanè, quod ſine oſtentation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dictum eſſe velim, ita ſum affectus, ut ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid in hoc opere minus verè perſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſſe ſcirem diſpecturus illud ſim, &amp; lectorem iple moniturus ultrò, ne fidem habeat. Sèd plane confido, futurum, ut nulla mihi vaniras objici poſſit, &amp;c. <hi>Sleidan. praefat. ad Elector. Saxoniae.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>a very learned writer tell the ſtory; and what both his credit and judgement was concerning the ſame. Now you muſt pardon him, if he do perchance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">Perſ. ſat. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Auriculas teneras mordaci radere vero:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And here you have his owne words, rendred as neerely as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently would permit. (n)</hi> Lindenius quidam <hi>(falſly printed for Leydenſis)</hi> Sarcinator, &amp;c. A certaine Botcher, ſaies he, of <hi>Leyden</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> having by his Sermons gotten to be King of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> ſtir'd up a rebellion of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort of people, <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>He meanes.</hi> Thomas Muncer, <hi>and his complices, whom</hi> Luther <hi>termes</hi> Importunos concionato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, <hi>and</hi> Sanguinarios doctores, Sleid. lib. 5.</note> as formerly others had done, who for ten yeeres ſpace deſtroyed and laid waſte <hi>Germany,</hi> and occaſioned the death of many thouſands. But here I cannot ſufficiently admire the ſottiſhneſſe of thoſe men, who placed over themſelves ſuch a King as preached no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to the people, but the deſtruction of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, the abrogation of Magiſtrates, and that all men were created by that great and powerfull God to a like
<pb facs="tcp:123366:4"/>condition. Who either from thoſe wild conceits he had gathered out of the <hi>Talmud,</hi> or other <hi>Judaicall</hi> forgeries; or elſe, from abſurdities taken out of the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> did teach them, that the enemies of their religion, or rather indeed of their rebellion and treaſon, were to be dealt withall by baniſhment, and impriſonment; by bonds, and ſtripes, and by death it ſelfe. <note n="(p)" place="margin">Fidem huic ſermoni res ipſa facit: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam mendacio iſta confingeremus, &amp; rerum ab iis geſtarum veritas noſtram oratto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem refataret.</note> The truth of the matter procures it ſelfe beliefe. And I could wiſh, that all were but lies, and meerely feigned; and that the truth, of the carriage of the whole buſineſſe otherwiſe, might confute what I ſay. At firſt, when this doctrine, newly raiſ'd from hell, was ſcattered and ſpread among the people, nothing could ſeeme more meeke and ſimple then theſe kind of men. They deſired nothing, forſooth, but <hi>Reformation</hi> of the old diſcipline, and <hi>liberty of conſcience.</hi> But, I pray you, what liberty of conſcience call you that, which breaking downe all pales and boundaries, endeavours what it can to ruine Kingdome, and Common-wealths, and to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe all manners and Laws? This conſcience is a wolfe in <hi>a ſheepes cloathing.</hi> And as the Sea-horſe, according to <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ib. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Plutarch,</hi> kils the ſire, that he may more eaſily couple with the dam; ſo theſe mad men, that they may with more freedome abuſe the Commonwealth, which is the mother of us all, to their owne luſts, they ſtrive to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enthrone, and put downe all Kings and Magiſtrates, who are the common fathers of the people. And as the Viper is not borne, but by eating out a way to life: ſo neither is this new profeſſion, but by the deſtruction of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, our mother. For, as <hi>Macrobius</hi> ſaies of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picures</hi> ſect, this whole faction, carried away from the truth with a full ſwinge, cannot by any meanes ſubſiſt, but by the corruption of manners and Lawes, and the utter ruine of States. For where good Laws are in force,
<pb facs="tcp:123366:5"/>how poſſibly can any ſcoundrell fellow <note n="q" place="margin">Abjectiſſimus quiſque de faece vulgi ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>do, impudentiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quiſque ſycophanta, perditiſſ. apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata, &amp;c.</note>, any dunghill cobler, any talkative, ignorant, impudent coxcombe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and aime at Principality, and a Kingdome, and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny it ſelfe? They, that were firſt indeed miſled by this way, might be ſomewhat excuſed, as being, through their folly and ſimplicity, enveagled under a faire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and ſhew of Evangelicall truth. But now, if any one at this day, and in ſo great a light of the Goſpell, ſuffer himſelfe at noon-tide to be blinded, and ſeduced; he ſhall not be conceived to offend out of folly, and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity; but out of ſtubbornneſſe, and incurable mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and therefore muſt by no meanes thinke to depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate that judgement, which he hath voluntarily, and with his owne hands pluckt upon his owne head. <hi>Thus far out of that learned man, the</hi> contrary minded <hi>Mr.</hi> Blackwood, <hi>if I may borrow the expreſſion, in his booke dedicated to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Prince</hi> HENRY, <hi>and inſcribed,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Of the bond of Religion, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> De Vinculo Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis &amp; Imperii. <hi>A writer, to ſay no more, (for it is teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony ſufficient) very highly eſteemed of, for his</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">In his Speech of the <hi>Poſt-nati.</hi>
               </note> ſingular learning, <hi>by that great and eminent Lawyer, Chancellour</hi> Egerton L. Elleſmere.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <q>
               <bibl>JUDG. 9.15.</bibl> And the <hi>bramble</hi> ſaid unto the Trees, If in truth ye anoint me King over you, then come, and put your truſt in my ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow; and if not, let fire come out of the Bramble, and devour the <hi>Cedars</hi> of <hi>Lebanon.</hi>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:123366:5"/>
            <head>Mock-Majeſtie: OR, The Siege of <hi>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NSTER. Anno</hi> M.D.XXX.III.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OT farre from <hi>Munſter,</hi> one of the chiefe Cities of <hi>Weſtphaly,</hi> is a <hi>Church</hi> dedicated to Saint <hi>Maurice,</hi> wherein one <hi>Bernard Rotman</hi> in the yeare <hi>M.D.XXXII.</hi> Preached the Goſpell to a very numerous auditory. And when as the Citizens thought of ſome courſe to bring him in among them, they were hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Papiſts, who gave him ſome ſmall piece of money, to goe ſome where elſe, and exerciſe his Talent. He hereupon goes his waies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and having toucht at ſeverall places, caſting about for his beſt profit and advantage, after ſome moneths abſence, returns back to <hi>Munſter.</hi> They that were not well pleaſed there with, did what they could to keepe him out of the Pulpit: but to no purpoſe, the people were already ſo much taken with him. Therefore preſenly ſome of the abler and wealthier ſort got him in among them into the Citie: and finding the Church doors ſhut up againſt him, they ſet him up a Pulpit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doors in the porch. And being now become confident of their ſtrength, and preſuming on their numbers, they make bold to demannd the keyes of the Church from the Prieſts, threatning otherwiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to breake open the doors. Not long after, <hi>Rotman,</hi> by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and conſent of ſome, who were chiefe of his party, ſends ſetters into the <hi>Land-grave</hi> of <hi>Heſſens</hi> Countrey, being not far diſtant thence,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:123366:6"/>requeſting that ſome able, and learned men might be ſent to aſſiſt him in the plantation of the Goſpell. They of <hi>Marpurg</hi> ſent him two; who with himſelfe and three others, ſtraightway enter into conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how with beſt ſpeed they might rid all the Papiſts out of the City, that by this meanes the Goſpell might be preached with more freedom and liberty. The beſt way they could think upon was to ſumme up all the Popiſh errors: and ſo digeſting them into thirty heads, they deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered them to the Magiſtrates, aſſuring them all to be repugnant to the Word of God, offering to make it good out of holy Scriptures, even with the hazard of their own lives. Hereupon the Magiſtrates cite the Fryers, and Prieſts to appeare before them in publique, exhibiting the ſame Articles of their errors alledged againſt them. Now whereas they had ever borne the people in hand, that their Doctrine was according to purity, and grounded on the Word of God, which notwithſtanding thoſe Preachers denyed, undertaking to maintain it with their utmoſt perill; the Magiſtrates demanded of them, whether they could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute by Scripture what was objected againſt them. This being in ſuch manner propoſed unto them, as that they might well perceive thereby how the Magiſtrates ſtood affected, they anſwered in briefe, that they had nothing to urge for their owne defence; but that whereas hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they had made the people beleeve their Doctrine to be ſound and warrantable, all proceeded either from opinion or ignorance. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Magiſtrates, upon conviction of their falſhood, and errours in Doctrine, having nothing to anſwer for themſelves, but the bare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their owne lewdneſſe, commanded that for the time to come, they ſhould ceaſe preaching to the people, and yeeld up their roomes every where to theſe new Teachers, who had detected and laid open their ignorance and impoſtures. Afterward, by a joynt agreement of the Magiſtrates and people, they had each of them particular Churches appointed to teach in, which the Fryers in generall tooke very ſcurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but they eſpecially of the <hi>Cathedrall,</hi> being moſt of them deſcended of good Families. They, when they ſaw no other remedie, departed in an anger, making their addreſſe to the Biſhop; the reſult of their conſultations with whom was, to beſet all the wayes and paſſages, whereby proviſion might be brought into the Citie. Which being done, the Biſhop with the reſt, went to <hi>Telget,</hi> a ſmall towne ſome three miles diſtant from the Citie, to take further Counſell there. At length they diſpatcht a Meſſenger with letters to the Magiſtrates, warning them to ceaſe from their intended courſes, and to reſtore all things to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:123366:6"/>their former ſtate and condition; otherwiſe, that they ſhould be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as enemies. The Biſhop then was <hi>Count Francis Waldecke,</hi> and before him <hi>Fredericke,</hi> brother to the Archbiſhop of <hi>Collen:</hi> But hee, either for his healths ſake, or fore-ſeeing the ſtorme that was like to fal, had not long before voluntarily quitted both office and place; contented to lead a private life rather in his own Country, then to hazard his qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe among a factious and ſeditious people.</p>
            <p>They of <hi>Munſter,</hi> upon deliberation, detayned the meſſenger, and iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing out upon <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Eve, ſome nine hundred of them came unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly upon the Town, which inſtantly they tooke, beſetting every way, that none might make eſcape: but the Biſhop had departed thence the day before. Thus they brought the priſoners into the Citie, among whom were the chiefe of the Clergie, and others of very noble deſcent. The Magiſtrates demanded of them, what they intended to do, and whether they purpoſed any more to hinder the preaching of the Goſpell for the time to come? They freely anſwered, they would do what in them lay to further it. By this means they fell to an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a Copie whereof the Magiſtrates ſent to the Landgrave of <hi>Heſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,</hi> withall intreating him, that for the Goſpels &amp; Common-wealths ſake, he would not be wanting to help on a buſines of ſo great moment.</p>
            <p>Here upon he diſparcheth ſome to them, by whoſe interceſſion a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement was made; But all wrongs and injuries being forgotten, a firm peace was concluded of; that in ſixe Churches the Goſpel ſhould be taught; that whatſoever was unbeſeming or ſuperſtitious in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, ſhould be aboliſhed; that in the Cathedrall nothing ſhould be altered, that the Citizens ſhould not thinke that it any way belonged to them. Theſe Articles of agreement were ſubſcribed and ſigned with the ſeales of the <hi>Landgrave,</hi> the <hi>Biſhop</hi> and his Officers, the Nobility, Gentry, and people in generall, <hi>February</hi> the XIV.M.D.XXXIII.</p>
            <p>Things being ſetled in this manner, there came to <hi>Munſter</hi> one <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> an <hi>Hollander,</hi> and a Botcher by profeſſion, a ſtiffe <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt.</hi> He having cunningly inſinuated himſelfe into the acquaintance of the Preachers there, began at firſt, in private diſcourſe, to aske them, whether they thought it fit to baptize Infants? which they affirming, he wholly carryed with the contrary opinion, fell to ſcoffing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning of them. Whereupon <hi>Bernard Rotman,</hi> of whom there is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer mention, in a publike aſſembly of the people, exhorted them all to pray unto God, that they might enjoy the Doctrine of Chriſt in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:123366:7"/>not polluted with the corruptions of fanaticall and hot-braind men, eſpecially the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> who ſecretly crept in among them, and frequented their Aſſemblies: whoſe opinion, if it ſhould once but get the upper hand, was like to prove deſtructive both to Church &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. About the ſame time came thither alſo one <hi>Herman Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preda,</hi> who being appointed collegue, or partner in the Miniſtery with <hi>Rotman,</hi> began publiquely to inveigh againſt the Baptiſme of little ones.</p>
            <p>This fellow had been ſometime a heater of one <hi>Henry Roll,</hi> whom they of <hi>Vtricht</hi> had not long before this, put to death for his preaching of <hi>Anabaptiſme.</hi> And this was another degree and ſtep, whereby to advance this new doctrine; the matter being already brought to ſuch a paſſe, that all the talke of the Town was now concerning the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts.</hi> Yet what they did was all in private; none being admitted into their aſſemblies, but ſuch as were of their owne Sect; their Teachers likewiſe forbearing to maintain any thing in publike, venting their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines in the night time when others were aſleepe, then only perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their miſterious works of darkneſſe. But matters could not be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried ſo cloſe, but that the people muſt needs take notice thereof, who tooke great exceptions at it, and cryed out ſhame that new doctrines ſhould be ſowed and ſcattered abroad by night, as if they feared the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe and confutation of the day light. Hereupon the Magiſtrates made an Ordinance, that the chief authors thereof ſhould quit the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: which indeed they did; but were no ſooner gone forth, but they returned back by another way, being now ſo bold as to give it out, that God had commanded them to continue there ſtill, and to play their parts with a deale of bravery and confidence. This ſomewhat moved the Magiſtrates, and indeed ſtruck them with no ſmall wonder: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to avoid greater uproares and commotions in the Citie, as wel the Miniſters of the Anabaptiſts as of the Goſpell, are cited to appeare in their Towne Hall, and a ſet number of learned men appointed beſides. Here <hi>Rotman</hi> bewrais of what ſpirit &amp; temper he was, &amp; having for ſo long together kept himſelfe cloſe, he now in a generall concourſe publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes his opinion, and with a great deal of bitterneſſe, he declares the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of Infants to be a thing both ungodly and execrable: but <hi>Herman Buſch,</hi> a very learned man, ſo ably maintained the contrary in preſence of the Magiſtrates, that they by a publique decree were ſtrait way com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to forſake the Citie. They finding no remedie, pretended how unſafe it was for them to paſſe the Biſhops Countrey; whereupon the Magiſtrates gave them ſafe conduct and proviſion for their journy.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123366:7"/>But having formerly reſolved never to change their abode for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but to neſtle here ſtill, after a while returned privately to their proſelytes here, lurking cloſely in their houſes for a time. The Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in the meane while, before ſuch time as they began to peepe out of their holes, ſhut up the doores of all their Churches ſave one. For their feare was, leſt the Anabaptiſts, whoſe numbers daily encreaſed, having once more got the company of their Teachers there, might wholly ſhut out the Miniſters of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Vpon this in <hi>November,</hi> the <hi>Landgrave</hi> at the requeſt of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, ſent two Miniſters more to preach among them, <hi>Theodoricke Fabricius</hi> and <hi>John Melſinger.</hi> But <hi>Melſinger,</hi> apprehending the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions in the Citie, and the danger which might enſue thereon, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned home againe preſently. The other zealouſly exhorted the Citizens that they would heedfully beware of the doctrine of the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> in which courſe like wiſe he held on couragiouſly, and continued in it, till ſuch time as the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> getting the upper hand, made all flye before them out of the Citie, as you ſhall heare anon. And to make all ſure, as he thought, the <hi>Landgrave</hi> preſcribed a ſet forme of doctrine and adminiſtration of Diſcipline, &amp; that by conſent of the Magiſtrates and people: by whoſe permiſſion alſo <hi>Peter Wirtem</hi> had leave to begin againe to preach; but after a few Sermons, by <hi>Rotman's</hi> inſtigation, he was expell'd by the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> who being now become more inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and daring, tooke upon them to challenge <hi>Fabricius</hi> and others to diſpute with them. The Magiſtrates gave way hereunto, ordering withall that they ſhould uſe no arguments or authority, but ſuch as they brought out of Scripture, or the writings of Orthodox men; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing ſome ſufficient and learned men, who, as Judges, hearing and examining what could be alleadged on both ſides, ſhould decide the controverſie; and what they determined ſhould ſtand ratified, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all, for the ſpeedier aboliſhing of contentions and quarrells, and the reſtoring and eſtabliſhing of peace in the Church: but <hi>Rotman</hi> and his fellows would not ſtand to theſe conditions. When as therefore they would not agree to this ordering and deciſion of the matter in hand, they came to be ſlighted generally, and ſcorned by the common ſort of people. To waſh away which ſhame and contempt, they deviſed a more effectuall and compendious courſe, and it was thus. One who was ſufficiently inſtructed to act his part, was ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the reſt to counterfeit himſelfe inſpired on the ſudden by the holy Ghoſt, and to run to and fro up and down the Citie, calling out
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:123366:8"/>upon the people, as he went along, to repent, and be baptized againe; that otherwiſe, the heavy wrath of God would ſuddainly fall upon them all. What tumults happened among the people hereupon, is eaſie to imagine, every one that had been rebaptized crying up the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, and that too in the ſame manner. Many therefore fearing the fierce anger of God, ſo much threatned by them, were perſwaded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherwiſe men of an honeſt meaning, but herein betrayed by their owne ſimplicity and weakneſſe. Others alſo yeelded to them; but to no other end, but to ſave what they had: for the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> handled them that ſtood out in a very rough manner, turning them quite out of all. This hapned about the end of <hi>December,</hi> whereupon their Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers now began to look out againe, having concealed themſelves as I told you before, in their ſeverall lurking holes: and ſo gathering a great concourſe of people in the Market-place, they cryed out amaine to ſlay all ſuch as had not been rebaptized, eſteeming them in no better a condition then Pagans and Infidels. Next they ſeized upon the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique magazine of Armes, and the <hi>Court Hall,</hi> beſides the violence they offered to the houſes of private men, and thoſe of beſt quality. There were ſome, who to ſave themſelves and theirs, had got them into a place of the Citie, which was naturally diſpoſed for defence, and by this meanes they tooke many of them. This bickering with the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts,</hi> who had fortified themſelves in the Market houſe, laſted ſo long, till at length, giving Hoſtages on both ſides, they came to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; wherein it was agreed upon, that every one ſhould enjoy their own Religion, depart to their owne houſes, and keepe the peace for the time to come. <hi>Rotman</hi> in the meane while, and <hi>Bernard Knip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdoling,</hi> the ringleaders of the faction, although they ſeemed out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to advance the compoſition, yet under hand ſending letters to the neighboring Townes, they invited them of their own Sect, that leaving all they had, they ſhould forthwith repaire to <hi>Munſter;</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them withall, that what they loſt thereby, they ſhould ſpeedily regaine againe with ten-fold uſury. Moved by theſe large ſwelling promiſes, they came thither in great numbers, women aſwel as men, every one devouring great matters in their hopes, eſpecially they of meaner condition. The Citizens, eſpecially they of the wealthier ſort, perceiving the Citie to fill with ſtrangers, withdrew themſelves as conveniently as they could, leaving the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and promiſcuous multitude behind them. This was in <hi>February,</hi> a little before <hi>Shrove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide,</hi> in the yeare M. D. XXXIII.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:123366:8"/>The one ſide being by this meanes weakned, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> fell to chuſing a new Magiſtracy, all of their own faction. They made like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe two new Burgomaſters, <hi>Knipperdoling</hi> being one of them. And not long after, they ſet upon St. <hi>Maurices</hi> Church, firing it, with all the houſes neere it. Then they fell to robbing and ſpoiling all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches, eſpecially the Cathedrall. And after all this miſchiefe, in the laſt place, running through every ſtreet of the Citie, they called out upon the people to repent. Then changing their note, they war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all the wicked, (as they term'd them) ſtraightway to quit the place, except they had a mind to run the hazard of their lives. Then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king armes, they preſentlie forced all ſuch as were not of their owne Sect, out of the Citie, making no reckoning of either age or ſexe; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, as many women great with childe, miſcaried in this heady &amp; tumultuarie flight. Next they ſeize upon the goods of them they had driven out. And although this happened, but the day before the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop beſieged the Citie; yet ſome in their flight thence, falling into the Biſhops hands, were entreated no better then enemies; and it coſt ſome of them their lives, and among them one or two were Miniſters of the Goſpell. <hi>Peter Wirtem,</hi> of whom I ſpake before, being in ſome danger, was delivered by interceſſion of the <hi>Landgrave.</hi> The other Townſmen warned with the feare hereof, ſeeing what danger they that had left the Citie had run themſelves into, being well meaning men, were forced in a manner againſt their wills to ſtay there ſtill. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this time <hi>John Matthews</hi> a Prophet, for that terme they uſe, of high eſteem among them, commanded that every one ſhould bring into the publike what gold, ſilver, or other moveables whatſoever they were poſſeſſed of, threatning death to ſuch as ſhould faile hereof. And a houſe was publikely appointed for the ſame purpoſe. The people being terrified with the ſeveritie of this Ordinance, were fain to obey. And to avoid all deceit herein, by keeping back any part of what they had, two maids forſooth, and they Propheteſſes, were ſuborned, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to reveale whatſoever couzenage any one ſhould commit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Neither brought they together onely what was their owne, but their goods alſo were brought in common, whom they had turn'd out of the Citie. In the next place the ſame Prophet commanded, that no bodie ſhould have, or keepe by him, any other booke, ſave the <hi>Bible:</hi> that all other bookes ſhould be brought and burnt in publique. This commandement hee ſaid he had received from God. Bookes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were brought together in great number, and conſumed in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:123366:9"/>flames. A certaine Smith by chance at the ſame time, called <hi>Hubert Truteling,</hi> had caſt forth ſome jeſting ſpeeches againſt them they called their Prophets. This comming to be known, they called together the multitude, and appoint others to be ready in armes; here they accuſe and condemn the fellow: this mov'd the people exceedingly. The firſt that laid hands on him was the Prophet I told you of, throwing him down, and then running a pike into him, yet the wound proved not mortal, although he ran at him with his ful ſtrength. Then he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to be removed to another place, where he ſhot him with a musket which hee ſnatcht out of a young mans hand that ſtood by. But when as this neither could ſpeed him, he ſaid God had revealed it to him, that the time was not yet come that he muſt dye; and that moreover God had revealed his grace unto him. However hee dyed within a few dayes after. Hereupon the Prophet taking a long ſpeare, and running violently through the Citie, cryed out, that God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had commanded him to beate the enemie off from the Citie; but comming necre the enem es quarters, he was met by a common ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, who preſently ran him through. And although his predictions fell ſhort, and failed him now in a ſecond buſineſſe; yet his fellow Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets had ſo infatuated and be witched the people, and ſet out the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in ſuch a dreſſe, that they much lamented the loſſe of him; fearing withall, that ſome heavy judgment hung over their heads, having ſo worthy and eminent a man taken from among them. But <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> being alſo a Prophet, and of next eſteem to him, bids them all be of good cheere; for that it had been long before revealed to him, that hee ſhould come to ſuch an end; that hee would take his Widow home to himſelfe, and make her his wife.</p>
            <p>Two daies before <hi>Eaſter</hi> they ran into the Churches, and there fell a ringing all the bells at once. Not long after <hi>Knipperdoling</hi> propheſies that they who were now in high place and dignity ſhould be brought low enough; and that others again ſhould be preferr'd and raiſ'd from an humble and meane condition: and that he commands all the Churches ſhould be deſtroyed, maintaining with a great deale of gravity, that this Commandement proceeded from God himſelfe. Wherefore upon this aſſeveration, he was obeyed with a great deale the more cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and diligence. About the ſame time <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> delivers a ſword to <hi>Knipperdoling,</hi> &amp; orders him to be the common Headſman: for that it pleaſed God to have it ſo, that he who had lately borne the higheſt office, having been Burgomaſter, ſhould beare now the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:123366:9"/>and be no better then a hangman, he being ſo far from refuſing it, that he ſeemed to entertaine his new place with a great deale of joy and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
            <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> had for ſome Moneths maintained the war alone, upon his own charges: but now <hi>Herman,</hi> the Archbiſhop of <hi>Collen,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> Duke of <hi>Cleus.</hi> ſent him Money, Ammunition, ſome Troops of Horſe, and Companies of Foot. The Archbiſhop alſo came to the ſiege, to ſit in councell with them; and not long after they made ſome aſſaults upon the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in ſeverall places; but ſeeing no hopes of ſtorming it, they raiſed ſeven Forts about it, thereby to keepe all manner of proviſion from coming to them; intendng that ſome Companies of Horſe and Foot ſhould lie there all the winter. The Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> in the mean time demanding aids for the contimance of the ſiege, of all the Princes and Cities lying upon or neer the <hi>Rhine,</hi> as being his neighbours, and whom the hazzard and danger might in ſome ſort concern, as well as himſelf. Hereupon a meeting was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Coblentz, Decemb.</hi> XIII. M. D. XXXIV.</p>
            <p>After an aſſault made upon the City to no putpoſe, <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes himſelf to a ſound ſleep, and there for ſooth he dreams for three daies: being wakened, he vouchſafes no man a word, but makes ſignes for paper, and therein he writes down the names of twelve men, and among them ſome of the beſt Gentry that were left; theſe were now to govern the Commor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth in chief, and to have the ruling of all in his <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Now when as by means of this reverend Jury, he had made way to become King himſelf, he propoſes to the Teachers ſome certain tenents of his own deviſing, which he requires to have confuted by them by teſtimonies out of Scripture, which if they could not do, he would then commend them to the multitude to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of and eſtabliſhed; the chief of them was this: <hi>That a man is not hound to one wife,</hi> and, <hi>that a man may have in marriage as many wives as he pleaſed.</hi> But when as the Teachers ſeemed to impugne this his opinion, he cals them all into the Court, and that in preſence of his 12. men; here in a generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly he plucks off his cloak, and flinging it upon the ground, together with his <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> he ſwears, and beares witneſſe by theſe tokens, that this Doctrine that he had cauſed to be publiſhed, was revealed unto him from Heaven, and in terrible words threatens them with the heavie diſpleaſure of God, in caſe they conſented not. At length they agreed, and the worthie <hi>Teachers,</hi> for three daies together, preached of nothing but <hi>Matrimony.</hi> So he on the ſudden got him him three wives, whereof one was the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets <hi>Iohn Matthews,</hi> whom we ſpoke of before. There were others like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that followed his example, ſo that at length it came to be a matter of the greateſt credit, to have many wives: but ſome of the Citizens were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:123366:10"/>mightily diſpleaſed hereat, and giving notice one to another through the City, they called together all ſuch as loved the Goſpell, into the Market-place, where they apprehended the Prophet and <hi>Knipperdoling,</hi> and all the reſt of the Teachers. Which was no ſooner known, but the common people broke in ſtrait with Armes to their reſcue, killing out of hand ſome fifty of the Citizens, with ſeverall torments: ſome they bound to trees, and others to ſtakes, and ſo ſhot them, whileſt the chief Prophet cryed aloud, that they that made the firſt ſhot at them, did God very pleaſing ſervice: the reſt they put to other manner of deaths, but all ſavouring of exact cruelty.</p>
            <p>Towards the end of <hi>Iune</hi> there aroſe another new Prophet, a Gold-Smith, he calling the whole multitude into the Market place, acquaints them all, that it was the will and command of their heavenly father, that <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> ſhould be made King of the whole world: and that ſetting forth with migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty forces, he ſhould promiſcuouſly ſlay all the Kings and Princes of the earth, only he ſhould ſpare the common people; that is, ſuch as had loved ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and truth, and ſhould at length ſit on the throne of his father <hi>David,</hi> till ſuch time as the father ſhould againe require the Kingdom at his hands: that in the mean while the ungodly being every where ſuppreſſed and utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, the righteous generation only ſhould reigne in this life. This was no ſooner proclaimed in publique, but <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> ſtrait way fell down upon his knees, and lifting up his hands to heaven; men and brethren, quoth he, I have had, theſe many daies ſince, all this revealed unto me; and was my ſelf very unwilling to have it made known, but now to confirm it, the heavenly Father hath made uſe of another Miniſter. Thus he became King: the firſt thing he did was to abrogate the authority of his twelve men he had choſen: and as the faſhion of Kings is, he makes choice of his Peerage and Nobility to attend him: he commands likewiſe two Crownes to be made him, beſides a Scabbard, Chaine, and Scepter, and and other ornaments of Royall Majeſtie, and all of the pureſt and choiceſt Gold. Then he appoints ſet daies, on which he would heare all kinde of ſuits and complaints that ſhould be brought before him. As often as he came abroad, he was attended by his Officers and choſen Nobility: next unto him followed a couple of youths, both on horſeback; he on the right hand carried the Crowne and Bible, the other bare a naked Sword: his chief wife went in the ſame pompe and ſtate: For I told you he had many at the ſame time. In the Market place he had a throne raiſed for him, all covered with cloath of Gold. All actions and complaints which were brought before him, were for the moſt part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning wives and divorces, and theſe were wondrous often, in ſo much as many that had lived to a good age, one with another, came now to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for being man and wife. It happened as the people ſtood in the market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123366:10"/>thick and cloſe together in the croud to heare, that <hi>Knipperdoling</hi> get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up upon their backs and heads, and creeping along on his hands &amp; knees among them, and breathing in their faces, would ſay to every one as he paſſed, <hi>The Father hath ſanctified thee; Receive the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> On another day dancing in the Kings preſence, (for ſo wee muſt now call <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi>) <hi>Thus was I wont,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>in former time to dance with my whore; but now the Father hath commanded me to performe the ſame in ſight of the King.</hi> Being troubleſome, not knowing when to make an end, the King went his waies diſpleaſed. Then gets he into the Chaire of State, and plaies the King too, till the other returning in the interim, quite turned him out of his ſeate, and ſo into priſon for three dayes.</p>
            <p>During the Siege they wrote a booke and publiſhed it, calling it the <hi>RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STITVTION.</hi> Among other matters in this booke they maintaine, <hi>That the Kingdome of Chriſt ſhall be ſuch here on earth before the finall day of judgment, that the godly and elect ſhall reigne, the wicked every where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quite deſtroyed and conſumed.</hi> They ſay alſo <hi>that it is lawfull ſor the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to depoſe their Magiſtrates.</hi> Alſo, <hi>although they had no expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from the Apoſtles, for the uſurping of ſuch juriſdiction, yet they who were now Miniſters of the Church, ought to aſſume to themſelves the power of the ſword, and by force to conſtitute a new forme of a Common-wealth.</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over <hi>that none excapt he be a true Chriſtian indeed, ought to be endured in the Church.</hi> And more yet, <hi>that none can poſſibly be ſaved, that brings not in all he hath into the publique, reſerving nothing for his private poſſeſſion.</hi> Luther <hi>and the</hi> Pope of Rome <hi>they terme to be falſe Prophets, but</hi> Luther <hi>to be far worſe then the other. Marriage alſo they eſteemed to be polluted and impure, where the parties were not inlightened with true faith; accounting it no better then fornication or flat adultery.</hi> Theſe fond opinions of theirs have ſpecially been confuted by <hi>Melancthon, Juſtus, Menius, Vrban King,</hi> and that learnedly and at large, in their ſeverall writings of this ſubject.</p>
            <p>After ſome weekes, the new Prophet as I told you of, blowes a Trumpet through every ſtreet of the Citie, and commands all the people to appeare armed before the Cathedrall Church doores; for that they intended now to drive away the enemie from before the Citie; and being come thither, they found good cheer ready prepared and dreſt. Whereupon they ſate down, as they were bid, ſome foure thouſand of them; and after them ſome thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand more feaſted, who had been in the meane while upon the watch. The King and Queene with their followers were the chiefe waiters at this feaſt. Having eaten their meate, and almoſt made an end of their good cheere, the King comes and gives every one of them bread, with theſe words. <hi>Take ye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ye, decl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ye the death of the Lord.</hi> Then the Queene taking the cup,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:123366:11"/>gave it about ſaying: <hi>Drinke ye and declare ye the death of the Lord.</hi> After this, the Prophet before mentioned gets up into a pulpit, and thence he askes the people whether they would obey the Word of God or not, then they all affirmed they would. It is the command ſaid he then, of our Father, that ſome Teachers of the Word, ſome 28. ſhould be ſent abroad, who going forth to the foure corners of the world, ſhould preach the ſame doctrine which is taught in this Citie. Vpon this, he names ſuch as ſhould goe, and appoints them which way they ſhould ſteare their courſe. To <hi>Oſenburg</hi> were ſent VI. as many to <hi>Warendorf.</hi> To <hi>Luſat</hi> IIX. and ſo many more to <hi>Cosfield.</hi> After this the King and Queen ſupped with the reſt of their Officers, and them that were deſigned to be ſent abroad. In the midſt of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the King riſes, pretending he had forgotten ſome weighty buſineſſe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him in charge by the Father. By chance they had a ſouldier in their hands lately taken; to him the King goes and accuſes him of Treaſon, as it were another <hi>Iudas,</hi> and himſelfe cuts off his head: Then he comes againe to ſupper, and here he relates his bloody deed, paſſing it over with a jeſt. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſupper they that were appointed were ſent away about ſhutting in of night; beſides proviſion for their journeys, every one had a piece of gold gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, which they were commanded to leave in thoſe places, that would not admit of their doctrine, as a teſtimonie of their enſuing deſtruction, and everlaſting perdition for their refuſall of peace and ſo wholſome doctrine.</p>
            <p>When they were come to the ſeverall places whither they were directed, they firſt raiſed a great cry every where about the Towne, warning all men in generall to repent, threatning deſtruction to them otherwiſe in a ſhort time. This plain trick effecting nothing, they took their cloakes and ſpread on the ground before the Magiſtrates, caſting thereon the money which had been delivered to them: then aſſuring them that they were ſent by God the Father, they freely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffered them peace, which if they would entertain, they muſt bring together &amp; communicate all their poſſeſſions: if they refuſed this proffer of theirs, then that the piece of monie ſhould remaine as a token to witneſſe againſt their heinous unthankfulneſſe and unbelief. For that now the time was come, foretold by all the Prophets, wherein God would have ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to be obſerved over the whole face of the earth. And when as their King ſhould by the diligent execution of his office, have brought matters to that paſſe that juſtice might reign every where, that then Chriſt would again deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver up the Kingdom to his father. Vpon this their wild preaching, they were apprehended, and at firſt dealt with in a friendly manner; but this doing no good upon them, they were afterward queſtioned upon the rack concerning their faith and courſe of life, as alſo concerning the ſtrength of the Citie. But their anſers were, that they only were the men, whoſe doctrine was true;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123366:11"/>which likewiſe they would make good with the very hazard of their lives. For that ſince the Apoſtles age hitherto, the word of God was never taught aright, nor any juſtice to be found among men. That there had been but four Prophets at all ſince Chriſt; whereof two were juſt ones, <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden;</hi> the other two unjuſt ones, the <hi>Pope</hi> &amp; <hi>Luther;</hi> but of the two, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> the worſt. Being queſtioned why they forced innocent men out of the Citie, and from their eſtates, contrary to their agreement, &amp; promiſe paſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, taking into their poſſeſſion their wives, children, and all they had; and by what places of Scripture they could defend this juſtice forſooth of theirs? To this they replyed, that the time was now come, wherein <hi>Chriſt</hi> had promiſed, that the <hi>mock ſhould poſſeſſe the earth.</hi> That ſo of old God gave to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> all the goods of the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> After being examined concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the forces &amp; ſtore of come they had in the City, and withal about their wives they made ſeveral anſwers; but to the laſt that moſt of them had above 5. Moreover that they daily expected freſh forces from <hi>Frizland</hi> &amp; <hi>Holland;</hi> that as ſoone as they came, their King would iſſue forth with al his armie to conquer the whole world, &amp; ſtay thoſe Kings who had not adminiſtred judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; juſtice. After their tryal, when as yet they would not acknow ledg any other Magiſtrate, ſaving their own King, but perſiſted ſtubborn in their own, wilfull humour, they were all of them beheaded but one, who by chance made an eſcape.</p>
            <p>But now the City was ſo ſtraightly beſieged, that there was no paſſage out left any where. Therefore the Citizens fearing a famine and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the danger they were in, entred into a conſultation of laying hands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the King, and delivering him up bound to the Biſhop. But the King ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving notice given him therof, choſe out twelve from among al the multitude, whom he imagined would prove moſt faithfull to him to theſe he committed the chief care &amp; charge of the City, aſſigning them every one their particular place to defend, beſides theſe he appointed himſelf a guard to ſuppreſſe al kind of commotions and ſeditions that might ariſe among them. Having done this, calling the whole multitude before him, he promiſes them, they ſhould be freed from the ſiege, and all kinde of want which might enſue thereupon, before <hi>Eaſter</hi> next. But for his twelve chief Commanders. to them he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes far greater matters, they forſooth ſhould be Marqueſſes, and Dukes, and Princes, and I know not what, aſſigning them every one their Provinces by name, what Signiories and Caſtles they ſhould be made Lords of; reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving only to ſpare the <hi>Landgrave,</hi> for that he hoped, as he told them, that he in time ſhould come to be one of themſelves.</p>
            <p>Wee told you before, that there was a meeting ordered of the Princes and Cities of the <hi>Rheniſh</hi> Provinces at <hi>Coblentz</hi> in <hi>Decemb. John Frederick</hi> the Prince Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> came of his owne accord to this Aſſembly. After
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:123366:12"/>deliberation, ſpeedie aids were aſſigned to the Biſhop: 300. horſe, &amp; 3000. Foot for three moneths. Theſe forces, and the managing of the whole War was committed to <hi>Wirich</hi> Count <hi>Oberſtein</hi> as Generall. Here alſo they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, that other States of the Empire ſhould likewiſe be ſolicited for aides; And, becauſe the Emperour was himſelfe in <hi>Spaine,</hi> that <hi>Ferdinand</hi> therefore the King of the <hi>Romans</hi> ſhould be requeſted, that a publique Dyet, upon this occaſion might be appointed againſt <hi>April</hi> following. Then they ſent Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, earneſtly adviſing the beſieged to yeeld themſelves up, and to deſiſt from an enterprize, then which the Sun it ſelfe never beheld any more deteſtable, and to be abhor'd: withall threatning them unleſſe they did obey, and ſubmit themſelves to their lawful Magiſtrate, that the Biſhop who how beſieged them, and whoſe rights they detained, ſhould not want the aſſiſtance of the whole Empire for his juſt reliefe, and redreſſe of his loſſes. This was about the end of <hi>December.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They returned an anſwer towards the middle of <hi>Ian.</hi> CO. IO. XXXV. and that in many words, but nothing to the purpoſe: yet ſo, that they ſtill juſtified &amp; maintained what they did. As for what they were charg'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, about ſetting up a King, they made no anſwer at all to that. But in their private letters to the <hi>Landgrave,</hi> they indeavour to excuſe it, adding moreover many things elſe concerning the utter deſtruction of all the ungodly; and of the deliverance and Kingdom of the godly in this life. Withall they ſent to him the book I told you before they publiſhed, entit'led the <hi>Reſtitution,</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelling him to repent, and not as the other ungodly Princes, to make warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them who were innocent men, and the very people of God. The <hi>Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> having peruſed, as well their book as their letters, and himſelfe noting down with his own hand, what he conceived amiſſe therein, hee orders his owne Divines to make anſwer thereunto. And becauſe themſelves had ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied unto him in their letters, although but in few words and that too ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what obſcurely, that their King was not ſo much ſet up by themſelves, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and placed over by God himſelfe, he demands of them why they ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged not thoſe places of Scripture, upon the authority of which they imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it lawfull for them ſo to doe; withall what fore-running ſignes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies they had to approve and make it good by? For that God by all his Prophets, long before hand foretold of the comming of Chriſt; &amp; that with that evidence and plainneſſe, that not only the Tribe or ſtocke of which hee ſhould be deſcended, was manifeſtly expreſſed, but alſo the very time and place where he ſhould be borne. They had deſired likewiſe in the ſame letters that their Cauſe might have a faire hearing: whereunto the <hi>Landgrave</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, that there was now no place left for that; ſeeing that they had aſſumed to themſelves the power of the ſword, and had been the authors of ſo much
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:123366:12"/>miſchiefe and calamity; that every bodie began now plainely to perceive what was their main drift and aime, the ſuppreſſing of all Lawes, the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw and utter ruine of Common-weales. And that as their attempt for the maine of it, was altogether ungodly and execrable; ſo this their requeſt, to have a hearing of their Cauſe, was wholly feigned and counterfeit. That for his part, he had formerly ſent unto them faithfull Miniſters of the Goſpel, by whom without all queſtion, they had been rightly inſtructed. But whereas they now rejecting the wholſome doctrine of ſuch Teachers, had fall'n from their obedience to the Magiſtrate; had with violent hands ſeiz'd upon the goods and poſſeſſions of their neighbours; had taken to themſelves variety and choiſe of wives; had elected and ſet up a new King among them; had denyed that Chriſt had taken on him humane nature from the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> had maintained and aſſerted the freedome of mans will; had forcibly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained the people to a communication of their goods in publique; had deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed pardon and abſolution to lapſ'd ſinners; that in all theſe they had foulely violated the Lawes, as well humane as divine.</p>
            <p>They having received this Anſwer from the <hi>Landgrave;</hi> made their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and withall ſet him a booke, compoſed and written in the high <hi>Dutch,</hi> concerning the <hi>Miſteries of Scripture.</hi> And in their Letter they ſet a faire and ſpecious gloſſe upon their own cauſe, together with a defence and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of their opinions. But in their booke we ſpoke of, they made a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of the courſe and ſucceſſion of all times, of the whole world, into three parts or ages: That the firſt world, from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Noah,</hi> periſhed indeed by the deluge of waters: That the ſecond, which is that wherein we now live, ſhall be deſtroyed by fire: But their third and new world, which they maintaine ſhall be hereafter, is that, wherein righteouſneſſe and juſtice ſhall beare the ſway; but before this laſt ſhall begin to dawne and ſhed its light in the eyes of men, it muſt neceſſarily be, that this old one that now is, be firſt purged by fire; which ſhall not be neither, before <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and his power utterly ſuppreſt and trodden downe under foot. That then it ſhall come to paſſe, that the throne of <hi>David</hi> which was caſt down, ſhall be reared up again and eſtabliſhed; and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall again receive his kingdome here upon earth, and ſo ſhall all the ſayings of the Prophets be accompliſhed. That this preſent world is like the age wherein <hi>Eſau</hi> had the power and ſway in his hands; for that now righteouſneſſe and equity are put to ſilence, and the godly ones only afflicted: But as from the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> captivity, ſo from the great miſeries and calamities of this preſent age, there ſhall at length appear a day of ranſome and reſtitution, a day of freedome and liberty for the righteous; wherein the wicked ſhall abundantly receive the reward of all they have done maliciouſly againſt the Saints of God, as is fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:123366:13"/>and threatned in the <hi>Revelation.</hi> Now this <hi>Reſtitution</hi> is to happen im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before this bleſſed age of the world, which is yet to come; ſo that all the ungodly and wicked ones being ſuppreſſed all the world over, the ſeate and dwelling place of juſtice ſhall be adorned and beautified. The <hi>Landgrave</hi> having peruſed this book of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, imployes ſome of his owne Miniſters to write and publiſh an Anſwer againſt it.</p>
            <p>There was a meeting of ſome Cities of the Empire at <hi>Eſling,</hi> who among themſelves made a Decree and agreement, that thoſe who formerly met at <hi>Coblentz,</hi> had no power or right to impoſe any burthens upon them, for that the conſent and authority of the <hi>Emperour,</hi> and all the States of the Empire were to be required therein. Whereupon they wholly reject that Order, promiſing mutuall aid and aſſiſtance among themſelves, in caſe my one of them ſhould be called in queſtion, or indangered hereby. Withall they make <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> that whatſoever ſhould be ordered and decreed by the publike convention of the Princes and States of the Empire, in a lawfull manner, in behalf of the Common-wealth, that therein they would moſt readily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their duty.</p>
            <p>Now in <hi>February,</hi> there happening a great penury and ſcarcity of Come, inſomuch as many periſhed by reaſon of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nger and want; one of the <hi>Queens</hi> pittying the ſad condition of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in her diſcourſe to her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, expreſſed her minde ſo far, that ſhe could not once think it, that it was the good will and pleaſure of God, that poor people ſhould daily be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed in this manner for lack of food. The King, who had his Store-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſufficiently repleniſhed, not only for neceſſity and uſe, but even for Riot, having notice given him hereof, brings her forth into the Market place, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his other Queens, and commanding her to kneele down, ſtrait way he ſtrikes off her head, diſgracing her dead body, as if ſhe had been ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtrumpet. The reſt of them applaud the action, giving thanks to their heavenly <hi>Father,</hi> upon which the <hi>King</hi> fell a dauncing, encouraging the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple alſo, who had nothing left them but bread and ſalt, to daunce likewiſe, and to be merry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eaſter</hi> being now come, and no ſigne of deliverance yet appearing, the <hi>King,</hi> who had made them many glorious promiſes, to deviſe ſome thing; whereby to excuſe himſelfe to the people, for ſixe daies together counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits himſelf ſick: After this he comes abroad into the Market place, and there he tells them how he had bin riding upon a <hi>blinde Aſſe,</hi> and that the <hi>Father</hi> had laid upon him the heavie burthen of all their ſins; that now therefore they were become cleane, waſhed and purified from all their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And that this was that <hi>deliverance,</hi> which he had promiſed them, and that here with they ought all to remaine contented.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:123366:13"/>Among other things, which about this time <hi>Luther</hi> publiſhed in the High <hi>Dutch, Alas,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>what,</hi> or how ſhall I complain, and bewaile the ſad condition of theſe wretched and forlorn men? Moſt certaine it is, that evill ſpirits in abundance have taken up here their habitation and refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Howſoever, we ought deſervedly to praiſe the infinite Mercy, and goodneſſe of God herein. For although by reaſon of the contempt of the Goſpel, and the reproach of Gods Name, and the effuſion of godly mens blood, <hi>Germany</hi> hath deſerved to ſuffer the fierce wrath and diſpleaſure of God; yet for all that, he did reſtraine the rage and furious attempts of <hi>Satan;</hi> and ſuffered him not to goe on with full ſwing, and carreere; but in mercy gave us gentle warning, and admonition; And eſpecially by this <hi>Tragedy,</hi> or play, of <hi>Munſter,</hi> which had but little skill, or cunning in it, he fairly invited, and call'd us to the amendment of our lives. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt, except God had held him in with a ſtrong bridle, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſubtill a ſpirit, and ſo much his crafts-maſter, had certainly acted his part in a farre more dangerous manner. But now, ſeeing the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God had curbed him in, and abated his power, he rages not, and plaies his prancks, according to his owne will and deſire; but onely ſo farre, as the Divine permiſſion had given him leave. For this evill Spirit, all whoſe endeavour is to ſubvert the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Faith, would not likely make uſe of ſuch meanes, as to perſwade the marriage of many wives at once, thereby to effect, and bring about what hee aimed at: becauſe the hainouſneſſe, and foulneſs of the thing it ſelf, being confeſſed of all hands, he knew full well how all men, not yet bereft of their right reaſon, would abominate it, and cry it downe with ſhame. The Civill polity indeed, and government, may in ſome ſort be troubled and ſhaken hereby; but <hi>Chriſts</hi> Kingdome muſt be aſſaulted by other kind of battery then this. He that will undertake to inveagle, and draw men into ſnares, muſt by no meanes affect Empire and command, much leſſe act the <hi>Tyrant.</hi> This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deteſted alike by all men, and all eyes being broad open to obſerve and interpret whereto ſuch counſells tend; they muſt goe to worke by more hidden meanes, as is were by-way pathes, if they intend their deſignes ſhall obtaine wiſhed for iſſue, and take effect. A ſordid and uncouth at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, a behaviour of the countenance to compoſedneſs, and auſterity; a hanging of the head, with dejected looks; frequent faſtings, and an utter refuſall of the very touch of money; abſtinence from fleſh-meats, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; a deniall of obedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce to Magiſtrates, and a generall diſreſpect to all kind of temporall, or civill dominion, with an outward profeſſion however of extraordinary humility in themſelves. By theſe meanes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:123366:14"/>and by ſuch cloſe policy as this, even wiſe men have been over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; and by ſuch dark, and myſterious courſes, ſome have made a way and entrance to great ſway and Power. But, as here, by extream impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to arrogate and uſurpe the power of a <hi>King,</hi> and according to the unrulineſſe of unbounded luſt, to take away wives; that this was the trick of ſome ſhallow and untaught <hi>Devill;</hi> or elſe, if hee had all his cunning, and ſl ghts about him, that he was ſo fetter'd, and chain'd by an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtering Power, that he c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld not make uſe of his tricks at his own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Which no doubt God does to no other end, then that wee ſhould entertaine a more reverentiall reſpect of the <hi>Divine</hi> Providence, and be the ſooner excited to Repentance, and amendment of our wayes, before <hi>God</hi> give him liberty for the full ex rciſe of his practiſes; who certainly then will ſet upon ut wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h redoubled forces. For if this ſame poore, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible <hi>Scribe-Devill,</hi> can of himſelf raiſe ſuch Tumults and Vproares; what ſhall we doe, when the <hi>great Devill</hi> himſelf, with all his knowledge and Arts about him, ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll come with full ſaile againſt us, and give us a broad-ſide; being both a <hi>cunning Lawyer,</hi> and a <hi>crafty Divine?</hi> Wherefore no ſuch great feare, or thought, ought to be entertained concerning this ſo untrim, and untutor'd a <hi>Devill.</hi> Beſides I am fully perſwaded, that this <hi>Paegeant,</hi> and <hi>meck-ſhow</hi> is not ſo well approved of by all in the City; but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t it occaſions great grief, and ſad thoughts of heart, to moſt there; who no doubt with teares, and ſighes, daily Petition for, and expect a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from Gods hands; as formerly happened in that tumultuary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Ruſticks, and ill adviſed people, lately among us. And I could w ſh from my heart, that there were no ſpirit in the whole world, more cunning, and crafty then is this <hi>Munſter-Devill:</hi> For ſo long as God doth not quite take away his Word and Goſpel from among us, there can certainely be but few, and thoſe not very wiſe, who will ſuffer themſelves to be drawne away by ſo ſot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſh and unſober a maſter. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I muſt confeſſe, that when the wrath and anger of God is kindled againſt any people, there is no errour ſo unreaſonable or abſurd, which the <hi>Devill</hi> cannot eaſily perſwade them unto; as wee plain y ſee it happened in the Doctrine of <hi>Mahomet.</hi> For though the whole compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and frame thereof, be but a continued piece of extreame folly, and ſenſuality, yet upon the removall, or rather putting out of the divine light of Gods Word among them, it aſſumed to it ſelfe that ſtrength and vigor, and ſpread it ſelf to that large extent and power, which at this day <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome</hi> beholds, and witneſſes, with no leſſe wonderment them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. And indeed, except <hi>God</hi> had by his Goodneſſe and Providence, repreſſed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:123366:14"/>the attempts and inſolencies of <hi>Muncer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thomas M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cer. Sleida<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> l. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Germany</hi> had now been in no better a condition. For although the <hi>Devill,</hi> by Gods permiſſion, can ſometimes blow a ſmall ſpark into a generall flame, and ſcath-fire; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever there is no more compendious way of extinguiſhing it, then by the Word of God. For ſeeing all the Armour of our enemy is uncorporeall, and ſpirituall, it is not Troopes of Horſes, or other warlike preparations, that can quell and overcome him. Now as for thoſe Bookes written, and publiſhed by them of <hi>Munſter,</hi> wherein in lively colours they paint, and ſet forth to view their owne folly and madneſſe; In the firſt place, their Doctrines containe in them extreme forpperies, and abſurdities; and that in matters of faith. For ſpeaking of Chriſt, they ſay hee is not <hi>ſprung</hi> of the ſeed of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> to uſe their own words; although they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs him to come of the ſeed of <hi>David.</hi> Here they unfold not the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſufficiently, as it requires. And certainly the Devill herein conceales ſome monſtrous myſtery for his owne ends, intimating unto us, and that too not obſcurely, that the ſeed or fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh of <hi>Mary,</hi> can not deliver and ſave u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. But hee loſes his labour: For the Scripture tells us, that Chriſt was <hi>borne</hi> of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which word in all Languages,<note place="margin">Iſai. 11.1. Gal. 4.4.</note> is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the Childe, which being conceived and faſhioned of the fleſh of the Mother, is brought forth into the World. Againe, whereas they condemne <hi>former Baptiſme,</hi> as profane and unholy; therein alſo they ſhew their little skill. For they conceive, and think of it, not as a thing of Gods appointment, but onely as the worke of man. Wherefore if what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the wicked conferre or receive, ought thus to be ſlighted and reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; I wonder indeed why they alſo refute not, and fling away, gold, and ſilver, and other treaſures, plundred from the ungodly; and deviſe not, and coine for themſelves ſome new invented materialle. For <hi>Baptiſme</hi> is the worke and creature of God, as well as all theſe. When an ungodly man ſweares, hee does wrong to the Name of God: but if the Name of God be not a true Name to him, he offends not. He that robs or ſteales, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits rapine, breakes the Law of God: But if the Law be not a true Law to him, hee treſpaſses not. So alſo, if the former <hi>Baptiſme</hi> be nothing, neither doe they ſinne any thing that are baptized therewith. Why therefore doe they deteſt this <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> as an ungodly thing, when as according to their own confeſſion, it is nothing? If the <hi>Marriages</hi> of former times are, as they ſay, to be accounted for fornication, and adultery, ſeeing they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, as they will have it, by thoſe that wanted faith; doe not they, I pray you, confeſſe themſelves to be the children of Harlots? Now if they be illegitimate, and baſtards, I would faine know, by what right they come
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:123366:15"/>to inherit, and enjoy the priviledge of thoſe places they live in? Truly it would be but reaſon, ſeeing they are ſuch, that they ſhould be made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of inheriting; and that in this their new way of marriage, they ſhould find themſelves alſo ſome new meanes and poſſeſſions, which as leaſt may have a fairer and honeſter title. For it is not ſeemly methinks, that ſuch good and godly men forſooth, ſhould maintain themſelves upon ſuch whoriſh and unlawfully gotten goods; or elſe be forced, poor ſoules! by plaine violence, and robbery, to pillage and plunder from other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. As for that ridiculous <hi>Kingdome</hi> of theirs, which they creame of, there are ſo many, and ſo mani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt impieties in this one buſineſſe alone, that I need not make any more words of it: and indeed perhaps, what I have already ſaid concerning it, may be thought unneceſſary, and too much; eſpecially ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole ſubject thereof hath abundantly enough been diſcuſſed, and laid open, by the labours of other men.</p>
            <p>At the <hi>Dyet,</hi> which at the requeſt of the Princes of the Empire, <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of the <hi>Romanes</hi> held by his Deputies at <hi>Wormes</hi> in <hi>Aprill,</hi> the Cities which hitherto had contributed no monies to the Warre, in the firſt place made their Proteſtation, that they appeared not here, out of any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Decree paſſed at <hi>Coblentz;</hi> but out of obedience to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and King <hi>Ferdinand.</hi> Whereupon there happened a great debate between them, and the Princes about the contribution. At length ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies were appointed for five moneths; and twenty thouſand Crownes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to be paid in monethly. Likewiſe it was decreed, that upon ſtorm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or taking in of the City, the innocent people ſhould be ſpared; and that honeſt men, who were either kept in by the Siege, or had formerly quitted the place, ſhould have their goods reſtored them. Upon the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of this Decree, the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> delivers over his Army to the command of <hi>Oberſtein.</hi> But theſe publike ſummes being negligently col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and indeed not before it was too late, the Generall was not able to performe any extraordinary ſervice. Beſides, the Commanders, in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall mutiny of the Souldiers for want of pay, were many times brought in hazard of their lives.</p>
            <p>But when as things were brought to that wretched and lamentable paſſe within the City, that very many died daily of the famine; and many al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſtole away, and ſcap'd from thence, but ſo ſtarv'd and ſpent with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that they were pitied by their very enemies, into whoſe hands they ſell; The Commanders perſwaded, and promis'd the Townſ-men, that if they would deliver up their <hi>King,</hi> and ſome few more beſides, they ſhould be excuſed from all particular, as well dammage and danger.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:123366:15"/>The Citizens, although they were wondrous willing ſo to doe, yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terr'd by the cruelty, and watchfulneſſe of their King, they durſt not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing. For he for his part, was ſo reſolute and obſtinate, that ſo long as any thing was left, whereupon himſelf, and ſome few others might be kept alive, he never intended to yeeld up the Town. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders therfore in the Army ſend to them the ſecond time, and forewarn them, that they ſend out no more, no not ſo much as women, or children. This was the firſt of <hi>Iune.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next day, they of the Towne returne an Anſwer; complaining, that they could not be admitted to a lawfull hearing; adding withall, how hardly, and grievouſly they were dealt with, and that without any deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on their parts at all; That if any body would take upon him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate their errour, they would be ready in all dutifull manner to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it. Then they expound a place in <hi>Daniel,</hi> concerning the <hi>fourth Beaſt,</hi> which was far the fierceſt of all the reſt.<note place="margin">Dan. 7.7.</note> But their Letters end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this cloſe, that by the helpe and aſſiſtance of God, they would continue in the confeſſion of that Truth, which hitherto they had main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. Now all this was pen'd according as the King had appointed, and directed it.</p>
            <p>Things in the City being brought to this extremity, and as it were to the laſt caſt, there were two men, who had made an eſcape thence, who falling into the Souldiers hands, one of them paſſing his owne word for his faithfulneſſe, was ſuffered to goe to the Biſhop; and both of them ſet downe a way how to gaine the City. <hi>Oberſtein,</hi> and the Biſhop having heard what theſe fugitives could ſay, entred into Counſell thereupon, and <hi>Iune</hi> the 22, demanding a Treaty with the Towneſmen, they exhort and perſwade them to yeeld themſelves, and ſave alive the multitude, which by this time was ready to periſh with famine. They, their King being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, made anſwer by <hi>Rotman;</hi> but ſo, as that they meant not to forgo their former reſolution.</p>
            <p>Two daies after, about eleven of the clock at night, <hi>Oberſtein,</hi> without any noiſe, draws up ſome of his forces cloſe to the City, and by meanes of one of the fugitives, ſome Souldiers choſen of purpoſe, creeping along the Trench, at length got into their worked, killing the <hi>Corp du Garde.</hi> Others followed cloſe at their heeles, and finding a ſmall gate open, ſome five hundred of them, with ſome Officers and Colours, got into the City. But the Towns-men gathering into a body, ſtopt the paſſage, that the reſt could not breake in; and yet with much adoe it was that they kept them out. So making good the gate againe, they ſtraightway affaulted them
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:123366:16"/>that firſt made the breach and entry, and ſlew many of them. Thus for an hour or two, there continued an eager skirmiſh on both ſides. But they that were ſhut in, finding by chance another gate, with no ſtrong guard at is, forc'd it open, and ſo made an entrance for their fellows, who preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly broke in like a ſea. Howſoever at firſt the Townſmen made head againſt them, fortifying themſelves in the Market-place. But at length deſpairing, having loſt many of their men at the firſt encounter, they all cryed out for Quarter, which was readily granted them. At this very bout the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Knipper doling</hi> were taken. <hi>Rotman</hi> forſaking all hopes of life, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning deſperately into the thickeſt of the enemies, was ſlaine; utterly refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> himſelf alive into their hands.</p>
            <p>The City thus taken, the Biſhop ſeiz'd upon halfe the booty, and the Ammunition belonging to it: and ſo diſmiſſing the Army, hee onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd two companies as a guard for his own perſon.</p>
            <p>There was this yeere in <hi>Iuly,</hi> another dyet alſo of the Empire held at <hi>Wormes,</hi> wherein K. <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> by his Deputies, made a motion, that now the City was taken, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> through the whole Empire, ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where be deſtroyed and made away. Alſo that the Princes would move the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> for a Generall Councell. They made reply, that order had been taken by former Edicts, what was thought fit to be done with the <hi>Anabaptiſts:</hi> And as for a Generall Councell, that the <hi>Emperour</hi> himſelf had divers times ſolliciced the Pope therein; and that therefore, for their pares, they could ſay no more to it. At the ſame meeting, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> demanded reparation of dammages, and the coſts he had been at during the warre; complaining withall, that the monies agreed upon, had not as yet been paid in to him.</p>
            <p>When as nothing could certainly be determined of, there being but few of the Princes and States there preſent, another Dyet was appointed there, to begin the next <hi>November</hi> following, where then ſhould be a full hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, both concerning the Account and expences of the War; and alſo it ſhould be determined, what forme of Government ſhould be eſtabliſhed In the City for the time to come. When the appointed day was come, King <hi>Ferdinand's</hi> Embaſſadour firſt relates, and makes known the cauſes of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſent Aſſembly, and moves among other things, that they would conclude upon an agreement, that the City now lately regained, might con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, and enjoy its former Religion. The Biſhops Agent layes open and decla es, how great charges &amp; expences he had been at for the whole time of the War; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w great a debt he had contracted thereby; how having regained the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y, to prevent more ſtirre and danger, hee was conſtrained
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:123366:16"/>to raiſe two fortreſſes within it, and to put Garriſons in them; of all which he deſired that a ſpeedy conſideration might be had. Hereto anſwer was made; That the Biſhop had taken into his hands, as well the greater part of the booty, and all the Ammunition, as the Citizens goods; all which belong'd to the common right of the Empire; that it was fitting an even eſtimate being made, that all this ſhould be conſidered in the bill and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his expences: and what elſe was deſired, ſhould have a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and faire conſideration had of it. Next it was determined, that the Biſhoprick of <hi>Munſter</hi> ſhould be at the diſpoſing of the Empire, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the antient cuſtome, That all the Nobility, Gentry, and Citizens, except ſuch as were <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> ſhould be ſuffered to returne, and freely to enjoy their owne; That the Biſhop ſhould order matters of Religion, according to the <hi>Decrees</hi> of the Empire: That at the Spring next enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Agents of the ſeverall States, and Princes, ſhould meet at <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and there taking-examination of the Citizens behaviour, ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit the innocent; and levell all ſuch Forts and Workes, as the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> had raiſ'd: That the Biſhop likewiſe ſhould raze thoſe Fortreſſes he had built, and ſhould with all convenient ſpeed deliver out of Cuſtody, and puniſh according to their demerits, the King, <hi>Knipperdoling,</hi> and <hi>Crech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> who were his Priſoners.</p>
            <p>As for the Decree about the exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ciſe of Religion, the Elector of <hi>Saxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> the <hi>Landgrave,</hi> the Princes of <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> and <hi>Anhalt,</hi> openly declared, and proteſted, againſt any aſſent thereto: Some Cities likewiſe did the ſame; Neither would they agree to the laying levell of the old Workes about the City; as for demoliſhing thoſe lately rais'd, they made no great matter of that. The King, and his two fellow Priſoners were led up and downe the Towne in ſight of the Princes; and that more for ſport, and paſtime, then for any thing elſe. Upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and opportunity, the Miniſters that came along with the <hi>Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> entered into diſcourſe with the King, and diſputed with him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſome of his opinions; as about the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Magiſtrate,</hi> concerning <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme;</hi> of the <hi>Supper of the Lord,</hi> the <hi>Incarnation of Chriſt,</hi> and of <hi>Marriage;</hi> And by the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of holy Scriptures, they did ſo much good upon him, that though they could not wholy allter him, hee with ſome reluctancy ſtill defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his own; yet they ſo weakned him, and turn'd him, that at length he in a manner generally yeelded unto them; which ſome thoughs, hee did more out of a hope to ſave his life, then that hee was throughly convicted by their Arguments. For the ſecond time they came to viſit him, hee
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:123366:17"/>made them promiſe, that ſo he might receive his pardon, hee would bring the buſineſs ſo about, that al the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> who were in <hi>Holland, Brahant, ENGLAND,</hi> &amp; <hi>Friſland,</hi> in great numbers, ſhould be huſh'c and ſilenc't, and in all reſpects yeeld obedience to the Magiſtrate. Then they diſputed with his Companions, both face to face, and by writing, concerning <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification,</hi> the <hi>Baptiſme of Infants,</hi> the <hi>Communion of goods,</hi> and of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When they were brought to <hi>Telget,</hi> the King being demanded by the Biſhop, by what authority he had arrogated, and aſſumed to himſelf ſuch Power and Licence over his Citie and people? The King demanded like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of him again, How he came by any ſuch command, or right of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion? The Biſhop replying, That hee had it confer'd upon him by the conſent of the Princes, and People; <hi>Why and I,</hi> anſwered the King, <hi>was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thereto by God himſelf.</hi> The 18. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> they were brought back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to <hi>Munſter,</hi> and every one committed apart to ſeverall cuſtody. The ſame day alſo came the Biſhop thither, together with the Archbiſhop of <hi>Colen,</hi> and the Ambaſſadours of the Duke of <hi>Cleve.</hi> The two daies follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were wholly ſpent in wholſome and godly admonitions uſed unto them, to reduce them from their idle conceits. And the <hi>King</hi> indeed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged his offences, and ſought to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by Prayers, for the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſinnes. But the other two would by no meanes confeſſe any fault; but continued with a great deale of obſtinacy maintaining their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. The next day the <hi>King</hi> was brought forth unto an high place, raiſed from the ground, and there tied to a ſtake. Here two Executioners tore his fleſh with red hot Pincers. For the three firſt plucks, he was ſilent, and made no great expreſſion of what torment he felt: but afterwards inceſſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with a great deal of vehemincy, hee beſought God for mercy, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. Having been tortured and torne in this manner, for a whole hour and more, he was at length run through the breaſt with a ſword, and ſo dyed.</p>
            <p>His two Companions were put to the ſame torment, and execution. Their dead bodies were truſt up in Iron hoopes, and hung out for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like view, from the higheſt Tower in all the City; the King indeed in the middle; but ſo, as that he hung the full height of a man above the other two.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And thus</hi> Knipperdoling <hi>found his own Prophecy made good agains,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide pag. 8.</note> 
               <hi>and that too in regard of the ſecond part of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:123366:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
